A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 1994; 1998-2006
Library of Virginia
- IV. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2006., Extent: 8.40 cubic feet (24 boxes). (Box 65-804)
  - Subseries IV.A. Correspondence of Secretary Belle Wheelan (2002-2005) and Secretary Peter Blake (2005-2006), 2002-2006., Extent: 3.85 cubic feet. (Box 65-75)
    - 22 August 2005 - 5 October 2005 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - 6 October 2005 - 9 November 2005 (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - 10 November 2005 - 11 January 2006 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2005 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2005 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2005 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Mass Letters, 2004 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2004 (Box 137, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2003 (Box 137, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2003 (Box 137, Folder 4)
  - Subseries IV.B. Files of Sarah Finely, Deputy Secretary of Education, 2001-2005., Extent: 4.55 cubic feet. (Box 76-80h)
    This subseries is housed in 13 boxes and is arranged roughly alphabetically by subject/event. This subseries contains calendars, correspondence, e-mail, briefings, notes, presentations, and press releases. Notable subjects in this subseries include: Prince Edward County scholarship program (meeting notes, 8 May 2003 - attendees: Governor Warner, Del. Baskerville, Del. Watkins Abbitt, Dr. Vonita Foster, Dr. Ed Peeples, John Stokes, and Ken Woodley); Sarah Finley's Day Calendars, 2002-2005 (lists appointments); consolidating Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind; Council on Virginia's Future meeting materials and Cabinet Technology Team for Education and Technology (VITA), 2004-2005 meeting materials.
    - Achievable Dream, 2003 (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - AEL (Appalachian Education Laboratory), 2002 (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - Alleghany County/Composite Index, 2003 (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - ATE-VA/VACTE Schools of Education, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - AVID (Advancement Via Individual Determination Program), 2002 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Banks Associates - School Improvement, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Phyllis Bradley - Edutech, Inc., 2002 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Center in the Square, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Christopher Newport University, Masters in Teaching, 2003 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Coalition for Good Schools/Fairfax, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Coalition for Virginia's Future, 2001 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Constituent Contacts - Special Education, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Constituent Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 2002-2005 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - DOE/CTE, 2004 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - James A. Doherty - AP Courses, 2003-2004 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Derrick Douglas, 2003-2004 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Beverly Dunn - Personal Mastery Program, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - ETS - Chauncey Group, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - ExploreNet - Quality Teaching and Learning, 2003 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Governor's Schools, 2001-2002 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Harcourt Educational Measurement, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Highland County Public Schools, 2002 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Glen Hoptman, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Hunt Institute, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Individual Teacher Licensure Matters, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Jewish Women International's Prejudice Awareness Summit, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Lexington Institute, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Literacy Partnership for Reading, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Making a Difference Foundation, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - The McKenzie Group, 2004 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Miller School of Albemarle, 2004 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Reverend Tyler C. Millner, 2004 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Tim Moore, 2005 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - NAACP Call for Action, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - National High School Principal of the Year, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Olmstead Decision, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - One Number - Symbiont, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Joan D. Perry, Petersburg Schools, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Prejudice Awareness, Jewish Women, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Prince Edward/Brown, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Project Discovery, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Public Broadcasting Board, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Reading and Literacy Partnership, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Richmond Symphony, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Roanoke's Master Plan, 2001 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - School Evaluation and Management Services (SEMS), 2004 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Southern Regional Educational Board (SREB), 2001-2002 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Strategic Education Research Partnership (SERP), no date (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Time Travelers - Museums, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Tredegar National Civil War Center, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Association of School Superintendents (VASS), 2002 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Association of Career and Technical Education, 2002 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Council on Economic Education, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Education Coalition, 2003 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Foundation for the Humanities, 2003 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Math and Science Coalition, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Opera, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Virginia School Boards Association, Governor's Conference on Education, 23 July 2002 (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Virginia School Boards Association - Newsletters, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Virginia School Food Service Association, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Tech Mobile Chemistry Lab, no date (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Virginians at War, 2003 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Virginians for the Arts, 2003 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Vistronix, Inc., 2002 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Walk Smart, 2004 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Youth Matters, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Youth Risk Behavioral Survey, 2002 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Sarah Finley's Day Calendars, 2002-2005 (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Governor's Briefing, No Child Left Behind Cost Study, 9 September 2005 (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - The Governor's High School Leadership Summit, Richmond, Virginia, 8 March 2004 (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - The Governor's High School Leadership Summit, Richmond, Virginia, 16 March 2005 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - The Governor's Innovative Technology in Education Awards, 2002, 2004-2005 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Council on Virginia's Future, 2003-2005 (part one) (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Council on Virginia's Future, 2003-2005 (part two) (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Council on Virginia's Future, 2003-2005 (part three) (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Council on Virginia's Future, 2003-2005 (part four) (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Holocaust Museum, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Achievement Builders Corp (ABC) (Reggie Jones), 2005 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - ConnectGov, Inc., Cyber-Quest Learning System, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Princeton Review, College for All, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Venture Philanthropy Partners, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - Robert Glenn/Franklin County, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Literacy Foundation, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Status of Path to Industry Certification, 12 April 2005 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Capital One, Financial Literacy, 2005 (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - Internet Keep Safe Coalition State Kickoff, no date (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - CTE Salary Schedules of DOE, 2003 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - After School Grant, Mott Foundation, 2003 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Dept. of Education Management Review, 2002 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Health Care Foundation, FAMIS, 2002 (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Cabinet Technology Team for Education and Technology (VITA), 2004-2005 (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Staunton/Hampton, 2002-2003 (part one) (Box 80a, Folder 1)
    - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Staunton/Hampton, 2005 (part two) (Box 80a, Folder 2)
    - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Staunton/Hampton, 2005 (part three) (Box 80a, Folder 3)
    - Jamestown 2007, 2003-2005 (Box 80a, Folder 4)
    - Virginians for the Arts/Commission for the Arts, 2002-2005 (Box 80a, Folder 5)
    - Frontier Culture Museum, Zirkle Mill, 2004-2005 (part one) (Box 80a, Folder 6)
    - Frontier Culture Museum, Zirkle Mill, 2004-2005 (part two) (Box 80a, Folder 7)
    - Frontier Culture Museum, 2004-2005 (Box 80b, Folder 1)
    - Gunston Hall, 2005 (Box 80b, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 80b, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 80b, Folder 4)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 80b, Folder 5)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 80b, Folder 6)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 80c, Folder 1)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part four) (Box 80c, Folder 2)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part five) (Box 80c, Folder 3)
    - Science Museum of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part six) (Box 80c, Folder 4)
    - PTC Pro/DESKTOP, 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 1)
    - Regulations: Proprietary Schools, DOE/SCHEV, 2003 (Box 80d, Folder 2)
    - Regulations: GED Certificates, 2004 (Box 80d, Folder 2)
    - Regulations: Adult High School Diplomas, 2004 (Box 80d, Folder 3)
    - Regulations: Board of Education, Critical Shortage, 9 VAC 20-650-10, 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 3)
    - Regulations: Awarding of Verified Credits for Transition Students, 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 3)
    - Study of Federal Funding for Reading, 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 4)
    - Meetings/Events: Summer Reading Program, 2003 (Box 80d, Folder 5)
    - Meetings/Events: Governor's Science Event, 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 5)
    - Meetings/Events: Education Commission of the States (ECS), 4-6 April 2003, Atlanta (Box 80d, Folder 5)
    - Meetings/Events: Meeting of Virginia Congressional Delegation, 31 March 2003 (Box 80d, Folder 5)
    - Meetings/Events: Inside Business - Career Magazine, 2003 (Box 80d, Folder 6)
    - Meetings/Events: ECS/Southeast Teacher Quality Forum, 12-13 May 2003, Atlanta (Box 80d, Folder 6)
    - Meetings/Events: Recognition of Outstanding Educators, Governor's Luncheon, 11 December 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 6)
    - Meetings/Events: Governor's Awards for Outstanding Improvement on SOL Tests, 2000-01, May 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 6)
    - Meetings/Events: Governor's Speech to the Virginia Board of Education, 23 May 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 7)
    - Meetings/Events: Congressional Meeting on Education Issues, 18 March 2002 (Box 80d, Folder 7)
    - Digital Opportunity Investment Trust Act/Digital Promise, 2004-2005 (Box 80e, Folder 1)
    - Donors Choose, 2004 (Box 80e, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Summit on Extra Learning Opportunities, 20 April 2004 (Box 80e, Folder 3)
    - Learning Point Associates/NCREL, 2005 (part one) (Box 80e, Folder 4)
    - Learning Point Associates/NCREL, 2005 (part two) (Box 80e, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Tobacco Indemnification Commission, 2004 (Box 80f, Folder 1)
    - College Board, 2004 (Box 80f, Folder 1)
    - College Board, 2004 (Box 80f, Folder 2)
    - Globalization Conference, GWU, 2004 (Box 80f, Folder 2)
    - Jobs EQ, 2004 (Box 80f, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part one) (Box 80f, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part two) (Box 80f, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part three) (Box 80f, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part four) (Box 80g, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part five) (Box 80g, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Feasibility Reports to Governor and General Assembly, 2004-2005 (part six) (Box 80g, Folder 3)
    - Charter Schools, 2004 (Box 80g, Folder 4)
    - Charter Schools, 2003 (Box 80g, Folder 5)
    - Charter Schools, 2003 (Box 80g, Folder 6)
    - Charter Schools, 2002 (Box 80h, Folder 1)
    - Qualified Zone Academy Bonds (QZAB) Program, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 80h, Folder 2)
    - Qualified Zone Academy Bonds (QZAB) Program, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 80h, Folder 3)
    - Qualified Zone Academy Bonds (QZAB) Program, 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 80h, Folder 4)
- V. Planning and Budget Files, 2001-2005., Extent: 2.90 cubic feet (8 boxes). (Box 81-88)
  The Planning and Budget Files series is housed in 8 archival boxes and is subdivided by: 2003 General Assembly Session (2002-2004 Budget); 2004 General Assembly Session (2004-2005 Budget); 2006-08 Budget Development (Fall 2005; and Miscellaneous, 2001-2005. This series contains documents related to the development of the 2002-2004, 2004-2006 and 2006-2008 state budgets for state education agencies as well as related legislation. This subseries contains correspondence, e-mail, briefings, legislation, notes, presentations, press releases and reports.
  Notable documents include Agency Contingency Budget Reduction Plans (7, 11, 15%) for Secretary of Education agencies, October 2002 (Box 81, Folder 1). The FY 2004-2006 Budget Binder, 2003-2004, includes Sample Speech for Cabinet Members and Other Administration Officials re: The Governor's Tax Fairness Plan; and Message Point for Governor Mark Warner, 16 December 2003 re: The Governor's 2004-2005 Budget (B87, F3).
  - 2003 General Assembly Session (2002-2004 Budget)
    - Agency Contingency Budget Reduction Plans, October 2002 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part one) (Box 81, Folder 2)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part two) (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - 2004 General Assembly Session (2004-2006 Budget)
    - The Budget Bill, House Document No. 1, submitted 17 December 2003 (Box 81)
    - Presidents' Budget Framework, 2004-2006, 21 October 2003 (Box 81, Folder 4)
    - Proposed Higher Education Funding, January 2004 (Box 81, Folder 5)
    - General Assembly, 2004 (part one) (Box 81, Folder 6)
    - General Assembly, 2004 (part two) (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - General Assembly, 2004 (part three) (Box 82, Folder 2)
    - General Assembly, 2003-2004 (part four) (Box 82, Folder 3)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part five) (Box 82, Folder 4)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part six) (Box 82, Folder 5)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part seven) (Box 83, Folder 1)
    - General Assembly, 2003 (part eight) (Box 83, Folder 2)
  - 2005 General Assembly Session (2004-2006 Budget)
    - General Assembly, 2005 (part one) (Box 83, Folder 3)
    - General Assembly, 2005 (part two) (Box 83, Folder 4)
    - Budget (2005-2006), 2004-2005 (Box 83, Folder 5)
    - Governor's Budget Reports/Speech, 2004 (Box 83, Folder 6)
    - NSBA/VSBA Pass Initiative, 2004 (Box 83, Folder 7)
    - 2005 Budget Requests, 2004 (part one) (Box 83, Folder 8)
    - 2005 Budget Requests, 2004 (part two) (Box 84, Folder 1)
    - Budget, 2002-2005 (Box 84, Folder 2)
    - Project Discovery, 2004 (Box 84, Folder 3)
    - School Board of the City of Newport News, 2005 (Box 84, Folder 4)
    - HJR 105, School Construction, 2004 (Box 84, Folder 5)
    - Senate Finance Committee, Education Subcommittee meeting, 16 September 2004 (Box 84, Folder 6)
    - SB 1006, Protection for Children in Foster Care, 2005 (Box 84, Folder 7)
  - 2006-08 Budget Development (Fall 2005)
    - Budget Requests, 2005 (part one) (Box 84, Folder 8)
    - Budget Requests, 2005 (part two) (Box 84, Folder 9)
    - Library of Virginia, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Higher Education, 4 Year, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - SCHEV, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - Health Care/Nursing Education, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - K-12, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - Governor's Briefing, No Child Left Behind Cost Study, 9 September 2005 (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - Secretary of Education, Budget Issues, 2003-2005 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - Council of Independent Colleges in Virginia, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 8)
    - Commonwealth of Virginia Modeling and Simulation Initiative (VIMSIM), FY 2007 and 2008 Biennial Budget Request, 2005 (Box 85, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 2001-2005
    - Dept. of Planning and Budget, 2001-2003 (Box 85, Folder 10)
    - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC), 2002-2004 (Box 85, Folder 11)
    - Senate Finance Committee, 2002-2005 (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - Secretary of Technology, 2003-2004 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - General Assembly, 2002 (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - Legislative Agenda, 2001-2003 (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - Executive Agreements/Performance Measures, 2002-2003 (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - Education, 2004 (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - Governor's Budget, Review of Public Education, Dept. of Planning and Budget, 2002 (2002-2004 Budget) (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget Binder, 2003-2004 (part one) (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget Binder, 2003-2004 (part two) (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget Binder, 2003-2004 (part three) (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - 2005 Agency Budget Request Brief Summary Binder, 2004 (part one) (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - 2005 Agency Budget Request Brief Summary Binder, 2004 (part two) (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget, Miscellaneous Amendments, 2004 (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget, Miscellaneous Amendments, 2004-2005 (part one) (Box 88, Folder 2)
    - FY 2004-2006 Budget, Miscellaneous Amendments, 2004-2005 (part two) (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Higher Education Enrollment Projections, 2005 (part one) (Box 88, Folder 4)
    - Higher Education Enrollment Projections, 2005 (part two) (Box 88, Folder 5)
    - Higher Education Capital Outlays, 2005 (Box 88, Folder 6)
- VI. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2001-2006., Extent: 17.20 cubic feet (49 boxes). (Box 89-136)
  Series is arranged into six subseries and is housed in 49 archival boxes. Subseries have been designated for: A. Higher Education; B. Education for a Lifetime; C. Partnership for Achieving Successful Schools (PASS); D. Commission to Review, Study and Reform Educational Leadership; E. Teachers; F. High School Reform; and G. Healthy Virginians. This series documents the Warner Administration's extensive educational initiatives. The series consists of agendas, agreements, articles, background materials, briefing books, correspondence, e-mail, grants, handouts, legislation, lists, memorandum, notes, presentations, reports, resumes, studies, and surveys.
  - Subseries VI.A. Higher Education, 2001-2006., Extent: 5.60 cubic feet. (Box 89-104)
    This subseries is housed in 15 boxes and is arranged by project or event. Subdivisions are: General Obligation Bonds (GOB) for Higher Education, 2002; Governor's Higher Education Summit, 2002-2003; College and University Research, 2002-2006; Higher Education Restructuring, 2002-2005; New College Institute, 2004-2005; and Undocumented Aliens and In-State Tuition, 2002-2003. Subseries contains agendas, correspondence, memorandums, legislation, presentations, notes, handouts, talking points, press releases, briefing books, resumes, e-mail, reports, and articles.
    In 2002 the Virginia General Assembly approved and Governor Mark R. Warner signed into law a $900.5 million general bond package for educational facility capital improvements. On 5 November 2002 Virginia voters approved the bond package by a 73%-27% margin. Notable documents filed under General Obligation Bonds (GOB) for Higher Education include: administration talking points for the referendum.
    Governor Warner announced in his first State of the Commonwealth Address in January 2002 the creation of a Higher Education Summit to find ways to support colleges and universities and make them more entrepreneurial. He established a steering committee composed of administrative and legislative leaders, college and university presidents, and business leaders. The steering committee met 30-31 May 2002 and the committee divided into workgroups devoted to the four study areas outlined by Governor Warner: Administration, Management, and Governance; Planning and Capacity; Workforce Development; and Research Capabilities and Centers of Excellence. The Governor's Higher Education Research Summit was held on 1 May 2003 in Newport News. Notable documents filed under Governor's Higher Education Summit include: memorandums for planning/logistics of summit, meeting notes, briefing books, and planning session materials for meetings.
    On of the products of the Governor's Higher Education Summit was the creation of Governor's Research Panel to increase funding for research and development at Virginia's Colleges and Universities. Notable documents filed under College and University Research included: meeting materials for the Governor's Higher Education Summit held on 1 May 2003 in Newport News (memorandums for planning/logistics of summit, meeting notes, handouts, briefing books, planning session materials, prepared remarks for Governor); creation of a panel for a Blue Ribbon Review of Virginia Research Universities (resumes); and nomination packages from Virginia's major universities submitted to the Governor's Research Panel for review.
    The 2005 Restructured Higher Education Financial and Administrative Operations Act (Restructuring Act) granted Virginia's colleges and universities more operational autonomy in return for meeting state higher education goals and performance measures. The law began as a charter university proposal from the University of Virginia, College of William and Mary and Virginia Tech in 2004 - the schools offered to accept less state financial aid in return for more freedom to set tuition rates. The Restructuring Act required the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) to develop performance indicators to measure whether the institutions are meeting the state's goals; SCHEV approved the Institutional Performance Standards developed by the colleges and universities. The Standards were submitted to the Governor, who made some changes, for approval. The Restructuring Act also required the governing boards of each public institution of higher education to develop and adopt biennially a six-year plan and submit it to SCHEV, Governor and the General Assembly money committees. Notable documents filed under the Higher Education Restructuring include: background materials on the charter university proposal, review of legislation, legislation, meeting notes, reports, presentation, correspondence, e-mail, and materials related to the development of performance measures and six-year plans as required under the Restructuring Act.
    In 2004 a bipartisan coalition of state and local officials attempt to create a college in southern Virginia. The Harvest Foundation of the Piedmont pledged $50 million towards the establishment of a state-supported 4 year college in the Martinsville-Henry County region. In 2005 state and local officials propose creation of New College Institute, a publicly-funded institution of higher education located in Martinsville-Henry County. The New College Institute was established and funded in 2006. Arranged roughly in reverse chronological order; notable documents filed under New College Institute include: talking points, legislation (drafts of NCI bill), correspondence, e-mail, studies, presentations, reports, articles, notes, memorandums, studies for the new college.